Finding Aid for Aaron Finerman Papers 1950-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Aaron Finerman Papers 1950-1990, 1962-1989
Finerman, Aaron.
5 linear feet
Professor of computer science and director of the Computing Center at the University of Michigan 1978-1986, previously worked at SUNY-Stony Brook and the Jet Propulsion Laboratory. Professional and personal papers include correspondence, research reports, and material relating to development and administration of the U-M Computing Center.
9914 Aa/2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection came to the library from the University of Michigan Information Technology Division in 1994. Donor no. 7873
The collection is open for research.
Born on April 1, 1925 in New York City, Aaron Finerman graduated from Townsend Harris High School in New York City in 1948. He received a Bachelor of Civil Engineering degree from the City College of New York. He continued his education at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), receiving the S.M. degree in 1951 and the Sc.D. degree in 1956. While at MIT, he used the Whirlwind computer for his research, his first exposure to the emerging computer field. Finerman joined Republic Aviation Corporation in 1956 and headed up the computing and data processing division. Finerman joined the State University of New York (SUNY) at Stony Brook in 1961 as professor of engineering and director of a newly created Computing Center. Finerman also initiated the academic program in computing at SUNY, resulting in the creation of the Department of Computer Science in 1970.
In 1971 Finerman took a two-year leave of absence from Stony Brook and went to the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in California as manager of the Office of Computing and Information Systems. Finerman returned to Stony Brook in 1973 and stayed until 1978, when he joined the University of Michigan as director of the Computing Center and professor of computer and communication sciences. Finerman was director of the Computing Center until 1986. He retired from Michigan in January 1990, after a one-year sabbatical at Florida Atlantic University. Beginning in August 1990 Finerman was reappointed to active status as professor emeritus of electrical engineering and computer science and director emeritus of the Computing Center for several one-year terms.
Finerman was active professionally throughout his life. He received the 1981 Distinguished Service Award from the Association for Computing Machinery and was the ACM representative to the American Federation of Information Processing Societies in the late 1970s and early 1980s.
Finerman was also involved in organizing the Jerusalem Conference on Information Technology, a conference held in Israel beginning in 1971. Sponsored by the Israel Information Processing Association, the conference was devoted to computer technology and developing countries; one of its goals was to help establish Israel as a leader in information technology in the Middle East. Finerman was a member of the program committee for the first conference, chairman of the program committee for the third conference, held in 1978, and U.S. chairman for the fourth conference, held in 1984.
Finerman and his first wife, Gloria Blum, were married December 24, 1949. They had two children, Jay and Ann. Gloria died in 1966 and Finerman was remarried to Carol in 1968. She had two children from an earlier marriage. Finerman's son Jay died in 1979 and his daughter in 1980. Finerman died in 1994.
The Aaron Finerman papers document his career as an information technology professional. Organized into two series, Personal and Career and Professional Activities, the papers span the years 1950-1990 with the bulk of the material documenting the years between 1962 and 1989. The Finerman papers document his contributions to the emerging information technology profession. His papers offer insight into the differences between the worlds of industry and academia, as he worked in both. Finerman's travels and interests as documented in his papers also provide insight into the development of information technology on an international level. Related collections at the Bentley Historical Library include the records of the University of Michigan Information Technology Division, the University of Michigan Computing Center, and the papers of Bernard Galler, who was a close friend of Finerman.
Subjects:
Finerman, Aaron.; Jerusalem Conference on Information Technology.; Jet Propulsion Laboratory (U.S.); Republic Aviation Corporation.; State University of New York at Stony Brook.; T and B Computing, Inc.; University of Michigan. Computing Center.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Finerman, Aaron.; Republic Aviation Corporation.
Contributors:
Chevion, Dov.; Galler, Bernard A., 1928-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series measures .5 feet and includes biographical information, Finerman's notes from classes he took as a graduate student at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and one folder of correspondence, some of which overlaps with his professional career and work. There are four journals within this series documenting Finerman's travels to other countries on professional matters. He recorded logistical details and thoughts on other issues such as computer installations and meetings he had with others.
  - Biographical Data (Box 1)
  - Class Notes
    - Concrete Design 1950 (Box 1)
    - Indeterminate Structures undated (Box 1)
    - Polygonal Rings and Complementary Energy undated (Box 1)
    - Soil Mechanics 1950 (Box 1)
    - Structural Design 1951 (Box 1)
    - Structural Mechanics 1950 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Notes 1953, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1958-1988 (Box 1)
    scattered dates
  - Journals
    - Latin America 1968 (Box 1)
    - Latin America 1975 (Box 1)
    - Japan 1976 (Box 1)
    - Taiwan 1978 (Box 1)
    - Israel (Box 1)
- Career and Professional Activities
  The Career and Professional Activities series comprises the remainder of the collection (4.5 ft.) and documents his work in educational institutions and industry as well as his professional contributions.
  - Career
    The subseries Career is the largest, measuring 2.5 feet. It includes files on Finerman's work at republic Aviation corporation, State University of New York at Stony Brook, Jet Propulsion Laboratories, University of Michigan and South Florida University.
    - Republic Aviation Corporation
      There is one folder of material on Finerman's first professional position at Republic Aviation Corporation which includes a report he coauthored, correspondence, brochures, and photographs of Finerman and others with computing equipment at Republic.
      - Reports, Correspondence, and Photographs, 1958-1961 (Box 1)
    - State University of New York at Stony Brook
      The one foot of material documenting Finerman's activities at the State University of New York at Stony Brook includes correspondence, reports, and teaching materials. This material provides insight into the issues associated with the rapid growth of a university computing center and the emergence of an academic program in computer science.
      - Committees
        - Computing Center Advisory 1965-1967 (Box 1)
        - Computing Sciences 1963-1966 (Box 1)
      - Computing Center
        - Correspondence 1962-1967 (Box 1)
        - Equipment 1962-1967 (Box 1)
        - Report 1965 (Box 1)
      - Conference
        - "Advances in Computing," 1966-1971 (Box 1)
        - "University Education in Computing Science," 1967-1968 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1961-1975, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Curriculum 1962-1965 (Box 2)
      - Israel 1967-1968 (Box 2)
      - Proposals and Grants
        - IBM Grant 1969-1970 (Box 2)
        - National Science Foundation 1962-1965 (Box 2)
        - New York State Science and Technology Foundation 1966 (Box 2)
        - State University of New York 1966 (Box 2)
      - Teaching
        - ESG 162 "Introduction to Digital Computers," 1966-1970
          - Exams and Assignments (Box 2)
          - Lecture Notes, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Jet Propulsion Laboratories
      Finerman's activities at the Jet Propulsion Laboratories (JPL) are documented through correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, and other documents. The year Finerman spent at JPL in 1968-1969 when he was on sabbatical from SUNY Stony Brook on a NASA Senior Postdoctoral Fellowship is documented here. The minutes of the Scientific Computing Facility Advisory Committee reflect the effort to establish policy and service issues relating to a central computing facility. Less well documented is Finerman's involvement in JPL's Mission Control work. Photographs are part of the documentation of two tours of the central computing facility that Finerman gave in 1972. From 1985 to 1989, Finerman was on the Management and Administrative Support System review board at JPL and this activity is documented through reports and correspondence.
      - Correspondence 1965-1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Computing Facility Report 1965 (Box 2)
      - Scientific Computing Facility Advisory Committee
        - Meeting Minutes and Agendas 1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Report 1969 (Box 2)
      - European and Latin American Professors Tours 1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Computing and Information Services System Project Review 1984 (Box 2)
      - Management and Administrative Support Systems Program Review 1985-1989, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan
      The bulk of the material documenting Finerman's career at the University of Michigan in his papers consists of coursepacks for an introductory class he taught on computer systems.
      - Correspondence 1979-1990 (Box 3)
      - Introduction to Computer Systems EECS 181/CS 181
        - Coursepacks 1987-1989, 4 folders (Box 3)
        - Exams 1987-1989 (Box 3)
      - Research Personnel Committee 1988 (Box 3)
    - Florida Atlantic University
      - "Computing for the Liberal Arts" Course Materials 1990 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Other Teaching Materials
      - "Structured Methodologies, COBOL, and Databases," 1981, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - "Seminar on Computers, Communications, Information Impact of Computing Technology on Research," 1982 (Box 4)
      - "Structured Methodologies and Fortran," 1983 (Box 4)
      - "Structured Methodologies and COBOL," 1984 (Box 4)
      - "Data Processing with COBOL," undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Formal and Informal Portraits (Box 4)
    - A. Finerman With Others (Box 4)
    - Others (Box 4)
  - Papers and Talks
    Finerman's papers and talks, arranged chronologically, are a useful source for following his professional interests and for his perspective on the information technology industry. In some folders, there is correspondence documenting where the talk was given or its publication status.
    - 1967 (Box 4)
      - "University Education in Computing Science" (Box 4)
    - 1968
      - "The United States University Computing Center" (Box 4)
      - Computing (Box 4)
    - 1969
      - "Computing Capabilities at United States Universities" (Box 4)
      - "Computing Capabilities at Argentine and Chilean Universities" (Box 4)
      - "Curricula in Computing Science" (Box 4)
    - 1970
      - "Undergraduate Programs in Computing Science" (Box 4)
    - 1971
      - "Education for Computing" (Box 4)
    - 1972
      - "Computing Capabilities at the Institute of Higher Education" (Box 4)
      - "Corporate Policies for Computing Installations" (Box 4)
      - "Education of Computer Managers" (Box 4)
      - "University Computing Center" (Box 4)
    - 1973
      - "Education in Computing Science" (Box 4)
      - "Philosophy and Contents of Training for Computing" (Box 4)
    - 1974
      - "Professionalism in the Computing Field" (Box 4)
      - "Proposed Training Program for Systems Analysts" (Box 4)
    - 1977
      - Ethics Book (Box 4)
    - 1987
      - ACM 40th Anniversary (Box 4)
    - 1989
      - "Computers in the Space Program" (Box 4)
    - undated
      - "Managing the Computing Operation" (Box 4)
      - "Structured Programming" (Box 4)
      - "Software Engineering" (Box 4)
  - Professional Activities
    The last subseries, Professional Activities, includes material documenting Finerman's involvement with the Jerusalem Conference on Information Technology. His correspondence with colleagues reflects his personality and provides the researcher with an idea of who Finerman's contacts were, on an international level, in the information processing profession. There is a large amount of correspondence from Dov Chevion, the individual in Israel with whom Finerman corresponded regarding the conference. The second activity documented in the subseries Professional Activities does not reflect Finerman's contributions as much as the products and business activities of TB Computing, an Ann Arbor company owned by Townsend and Bottum, Inc., a construction company. TB Computing offered computer products and services to the consulting, engineering, and publishing industries.
    - Jerusalem Conference on Information Technology
      - 1971 Conference (Box 4)
        - Correspondence 1970-1971 (Box 4)
        - Jerusalem Economic Conference Computer Committee Reports 1971 (Box 4)
        - Proceedings 1971 (Box 4)
        - Summary Records and Reports 1972 (Box 4)
        - Summary Report 1971 (Box 4)
      - 1974 Conference (Box 5)
        - Correspondence 1972-1973 (Box 5)
      - 1978 Conference
        - Correspondence 1976-1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Chess Tournament 1977-1978 (Box 5)
        - Panel Sessions 1978 (Box 5)
        - Program Planning 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Publicity and Fundraising 1977-1978 (Box 5)
        - Solicited Sessions 1977-1978 (Box 5)
        - Steering Committee 1977-1978 (Box 5)
        - Student Competition 1977-1978 (Box 5)
      - 1984 Conference
        - Correspondence 1983-1984 (Box 5)
        - Letters of Invitation 1983-1984 (Box 5)
        - NSF Travel Grant 1983-1984 (Box 5)
        - Publicity and Fundraising (Box 5)
    - T and B Computing Inc
      - Board of Directors Meetings
        - 1980-1981 (Box 5)
        - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
        - 1985-1987 (Box 5)
      - Business Plan 1982 (Box 5)
      - Prime Authorized Remarketer Plan 1982 (Box 5)